Guide to the Rice University Honorary Chancellor Office Records, William Houston, 1961-1968 UA 272
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Honorary Chancellor Office Records, William Houston
1961-1968
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Houston, W. V. (William Vermillion), 1900-
UA 272
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and budget records. Also included are one legal brief (John Coffee et al vs. Rice University) and printed booklets from the inauguration of Kenneth S. Pitzer and the Semicentennial convocation. The Certificate of Merit for Distinction in Physics presented to Dr. Houston is also included.
Biographical / Historical
Inaugurated on April 10, 1947, as the second president of Rice Institute, William V. Houston served in that role until 1960 when a heart attack prompted his decision to resign that office. In the Physics Laboratory he continued his own research, taught one graduate course, and worked with graduate students. In the spring of 1961 he was made Honorary Chancellor, which he remained until his death in 1968. He is the only person in the history of Rice to have had the title Honorary Chancellor.
Dr. Houston's duties as Honorary Chancellor were at his discretion. The annual budget of his office contained no more than his salary, the salary of his long-time secretary, and modest amounts for office equipment, supplies, and travel. In 1967 he was still teaching one graduate physics course and counseling six graduate students.
Because of his years as university President and his reputation as an internationally prominent physicist, he had formed interesting and well-placed connections which he called upon for the benefit of particular faculty members and the university as a whole. It has been said that he acted "as counselor, facilitator, mediator, and ambassador, all during a period of great transition and change for the university."
Honorary Chancellor Houston died in 1968 while traveling to attend a series of meetings of physicists.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of correspondence for the years 1961 to 1968 and budget records for fiscal years 1965 through 1969. Also included are a legal brief (John Coffee et al. v. Rice University), correspondence concerning the Rice University Semicentennial, and the Certificate of Merit for Distinction in Physics presented to Dr. Houston.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were brought to the Woodson 6-20-96 by Physics Professor Stan Dodds, who said he recovered them from the office of Harold Rorschach, also a physics professor and a colleague of Dr. Houston.
Related Materials
See also William Houston Papers, Personal papers, MS 426.
Index Terms
Subjects
Rice University -- History; Universities and colleges
Document Types
financial records; letters (correspondence); certificates; booklets; notes
- Series I: Correspondence and budgets, 243928
  - Commerce Program Review Committee, 1965-67, 243942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence 1961, 243941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence 1962, 243940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1963, 243939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence 1964, 243938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence 1965, 243937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence 1966, 243936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence 1967-1968, 243935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Departmental Budget, FY 1962 & FY 1963, 243934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Departmental Budget. FY 1964 & FY 1965, 243933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Departmental Budget, FY 1966 & FY 1967, 243932 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Departmental Budget, FY 1968 & FY 1969, 243931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Legal Brief (Appellees) John Coffee, et al. vs. Rice University n.d., 243930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rice University Semicentennial Correspondence 1961-1962, 243929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Certificates and booklets, 243924
  - Certificate of Merit to Wm. V. Houston for Distinction in Physics, 243927 (Box 1)
  - Printed Booklet: Inauguration of K.S. Pitzer October 10, 1962, 243926 (Box 1)
  - Printed Booklet: Rice Semicentennial Convocation October 11, 1962, 243925 (Box 1)